Finding Aid for Elizabeth A. Leslie papers, 1940-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth A. Leslie papers 1940-1966 1957-1963
Leslie, Elizabeth A.
2 linear feet
87121 Aa 2
Assistant Dean of Women at the University of Michigan (1958-1963), later Associate Director of Student Activities and Organizations in the Office of Student Affairs. Collection concerns various University of Michigan responsibilities mainly in the area of housing and oversight of student organizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Elizabeth Leslie (Donor no. 1604 ), 1967-1968.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Elizabeth A. Leslie worked as the Assistant Dean of Women at the University of Michigan beginning in the early 1950s, and as the Associate Director of Student Activities and Organizations in the Office of Student Affairs (OSA) beginning in 1962. Leslie worked as a coordinator for non-dormitory housing first through the League Housing program, and later in the Off Campus Housing Division of the Office of Student Affairs. Her work in the Office of Student Affairs also brought her in contact with the Student Government Council and other student groups.
In the Office of the Dean of Women, Leslie worked with women attending the university who did not live in a campus dormitory. In the late 1950s and early 1960s, female students under the age of 22 were not allowed to live in unsupervised housing.. The League Housing program allowed these women to live in private homes near campus. Many sorority houses began in the early part of the century as unaffiliated League Houses, but by the time Leslie worked in the ODW, most of the League Housing was for sorority members.
The Leslie collection concerns her various University of Michigan responsibilities mainly in the area of housing and oversight of student organizations. The papers have been arranged in two series: Student Housing and Student Organizations.
Subjects:
Leslie, Elizabeth A.; Sigma Kappa Sorority.; University of Michigan. Dean of Women.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Affairs.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Bacon, Deborah.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Student Housing
  The Student Housing series includes Dean of Women files and files relating to League Housing. The Dean of Women files include the handbook for the Assistant Dean and an Administrative Assistant, and a retrospective of forms and procedures used in the office from the late 1950s and early 1960s. There is also an internal study conducted in 1957, and a handbook for directors of women's residences. The League Housing files include correspondence with the house directors and contract, pricing, and inspection records (filed alphabetically by street address) for some of the houses. Of interest are photographs of four of the houses. These papers provide a glimpse of women's lives at the university in the last years of the university regulations governing their living arrangements. Also within the files are agreements between the house owners and the ODW on rental charges, and records of inspection tours.
  - Dean of Women files, 1958-1963, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - League Housing papers
    - League House Directors, 1941-1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence concerning League Housing, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - League Housing
      - Ann to Division (Box 1)
      - Elm to Hamilton Pl. (Box 1)
      - Haven to Hill (Box 1)
      - E. Huron to Madison (Box 1)
      - Maynard to S. State (Box 2)
      - Tappan to Thompson (Box 2)
      - 714 E. University to 1011 E. University (Box 2)
      - 1015 E. University to E. William (Box 2)
      - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Supplementary Housing, 1942/43-1962/63 (Box 2)
  - Off Campus Housing Procedure, 1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Office of Student Affairs, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
- Student Organizations
  The Student Organization series concerns Leslie's contacts with various campus organizations. Of interest are the Sigma Kappa Case files which relate to the case in the late 1950s of the national chapter of Sigma Kappa sorority which threatened to revoke the charters of two local chapters because they had inducted African American women. The series also includes two Topical Files containing material about a variety of other student organizations. The Ann Arbor Girls' Club, as one example, was organized for the "town girls" who were from the Ann Arbor area. The information on the Barbour Scholars mainly relates to their housing arrangements. The rules and regulations and some correspondence about the "J-Hop" will be found here, as will rosters of Wyvern, a junior women's honorary society.
  - Sigma Kappa Case, September 1956-December 1959, 6 folders
    - Clippings
      - "References I-IX" (timelines and university policies) (Box 2)
      - Student Government Council, 1956-1958 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1959 (Box 2)
    - Summaries and Regulation Handbook (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Topical File 1
    - Ann Arbor Girls' Club, 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Assembly Dorm Council, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - J-Hop, 1953-1961 scattered dates (Box 2)
    - Joint Judiciary, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Topical File 2
    - Student Government Council, 1961-1965 (Box 2)
    - Wyvern, 1940-1948 (Box 2)